[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio net SC radio
brings some relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software thanks for your
support this is Robert I'm at the
SF conference with Dwight Merriman
Dwight is the CEO and co-founder of
10gen the industry sponsor of the
DB open-source database
Dwight welcome back to software
engineering radio thanks I say welcome
back because Dwight was our guest
earlier on episode 165 which is in the
archives if you haven't listened to it
which we're talking about DB and
no sequel today I will be talking with
Dwight about database replication Dwight
let's start out tell us what is database
replication conceptually it's very
simple it's just a replica sort of if
you think of an a dictionary where you
want to have a copy of the data on a
separate machine so you know we're very
used to replication on a single machine
on multiple hard drives ie raid so
replication sort of at the database
level is really to multiple machines so
it's I have a set of data and I want it
on more than one machine and I want it
to automatically stay in sync okay
what problem are what set of problems
does replication solve yeah it solves a
few problems one is just data safety
right so if I have the data on a couple
machines it's safer than if it's on one
machine right so if if it's on one
machine and sprinklers go off on top on
top of them in the server you know you'd
be apt to lose the data even if you had
mirrored hard drives in the machine so
so data safety is enhanced in addition
you can use it to do disaster recovery
so if one the replicas
is in a different geography or data
center that's even better for data
safety right if the data sighted birth
ok the senator burns down
I still have copy of the data it's also
good for high availability so which is
slightly different right because my data
could be safe if the Machine just powers
down and later comes back up but it's
not available while it's down so by
having you data on multiple servers we
can increase availability of the data
which is important and and finally I
think people also use it as a way to
scale and it's it's not replication is
not a total solution for scaling it's
it's more of a solution in my mind to
sort of high availability and data
safety but you can get some scalability
of reads through replication to a point
I actually think that other techniques
such as charting or partitioning of data
are probably a more generalized in
solution to scaling than replication is
is replication also used if you want to
transform the data on the replica for
some purpose into a different form sort
of yes so I think you know you could
just read it from the source and do the
transformation write it to somewhere
else directly but I think sometimes
people will they'll have a replica on
which they do different tasks than they
do on the primary so they might do big
batch jobs on the secondary and things
like that so that is one pattern that
does come up so you have different
latency characteristics against the same
workload yes so so one thing people do
is they'll replicate across geographies
so that if you have a copy of the data
close to the client that that's another
reason to replicate you said replication
is not a total solution for scaling
could you elaborate on what you mean by
that
sure so first of all in rites
replication doesn't help you scale
rights because if we're going to write
let's say a new document to the database
or a new record to the database and we
have safe in replicas basically we're
going to do that right on every replica
right so so we didn't really gain any
scalability because we're going to do
the right end times so it's really more
useful for scaling reads where if I have
n machines they all have a copy of the
data and each machine has a certain
capacity I should get n times that
capacity and sort of reads per second by
having the replicas now that said there
there's some limits on how far you can
scale up that way one limit is just you
have to do the rights at that many
places so if you had a hundred replicas
it could be relatively inefficient to do
every right a hundred times
you know if rights were super super rare
you might be okay but if you had some
you know if you have one right for every
three reads it wouldn't make a lot of
sense to write everything hundred times
right just so that you could get read
scalability in addition that there's an
there's another issue which is sort of
cache affinity or lack thereof so
imagine we have ten servers and each
server has 64 gig of ram right so we've
got 640 gig ram in the system and that
we replicate the same data and to all 10
servers and let's say today that is
bigger than Ram let's say it's
terabytes so each server can process
requests but what's going to happen is
if there's a hot spot in the data is all
10 servers are going to tend to cache
the same most recently queried items
right so I'm not really getting 640 gig
of cache I'm getting 64 gig of cache
data and all the machines are caching
the same data now if you're very astute
as a client you could say well I'm going
to send requests for certain documents
to this replicas and certain documents
to this replica and and then you're
going to get some cache affinity and
then you're really going to get 640 gig
cache data however that requires a lot
of a certain degree of sophistication
and extra coding ID user so so so that's
a challenge to whereas with something
like sharding you kind of get that cache
affinity automatically how would you
characterize a system where replication
will be most effective versus let's say
buying a bigger server and putting more
memory on it as I think of it generally
I think of replication about safety and
availability and things like that and
redundancy and not so much scaling right
so if I wanted to scale and I need
something like sharding and have several
small servers instead of one giant
server right and and I think there's a
you know there's there's generally a
sweet spot in server prices right so so
up to a certain size you know the the
cost and the power of the machine scales
are fairly linear linearly and then
beyond that it gets very expensive to go
bigger or even impossible so we really
want to find that sweet spot because if
if you can get a bigger machine cheaply
it's nice because then you have less
machines to administer right but if you
can't get it in more cheaply than I'd
rather have more machines so you know
what that probably means is using a
fairly large commodity server right so
you know a server that's you know five
thousand ten thousand dollars not using
like a Sun server that's a hundred
thousand dollars that's not where your
sweet spot is so I'd rather have ten ten
thousand dollar come out of the Xenon
servers than one Sun service one hundred
thousand and actually if if if if the
scale up is not linear with cost I
should actually mean less than ten you
know I should be maybe four or five I
think your view is a little different
than view that I've think is more
conventional in the industry where if
you're talking about applications where
a lot of the data can fit in memory on a
single node and reads out number writes
that replications consider primarily a
means for scaling out reads
would you characterize your view as
being slightly different than that or do
you mostly agree yes and and I agree
that people do use replication to scale
I'm just saying that it's not
necessarily the optimal way to scale up
you know I think traditionally databases
haven't scaled that well right the scale
vertically but not horizontally so if
you don't want to scale vertically and
the database doesn't have ill in support
for scaling horizontally what do you do
well you have a couple options one is
you can do replication if you read heavy
and then you have multiple machines to
read from so it's a valid tactic but but
I think it's to some degree in that
situation you're sort of working around
the fact that the database isn't
inherently horizontally scalable the
other thing you could do if you had a
conventional database that that didn't
have that facility is you could manually
shard or manually partition your data in
which case you wouldn't be using
replication to sharp a to scale you
would be using partitioning or sharding
scale and you just be doing it yourself
where you're going with this that
replication and sharding at some layer
of the system are techniques that will
help a system scale but you would like
those to be inside the boundary of what
people call the database and hidden to
some extent from the DBA well certainly
hidden from the client user of the
database the DBA will probably have some
awareness of you know how many nodes are
in the cluster and what the replication
factor is let me ask my question a
little differently what is your view of
what a data server should do is it
should replicate and shard itself in
order to scale by just adding nodes to
the cluster yes and and I think in some
ways databases have traditionally been
able to do that with replication and
maybe not completely transparently but
without any extreme effort and and then
the but the scale outside has been
largely missing so let's talk a little
bit about the backup use of replication
as a backup solution could go into a
little more detail about where where
does that work best
yeah so if if you lose a machine and you
lose all the data on the machine if we
have a replica we still have the data
now of course you could instead do
backups but the the thing about backups
is there a point in time right so if I
do a backup every eight hours and I lose
the machine I lost the data from the
last up to eight hours whereas if you
have replication
you've lost the data for perhaps zero
time or perhaps a few milliseconds so
depending on how you've configured so in
that sense it's sort of like a continual
bit hot backup if you will if you want
to think of it in terms of data safety
so so that's good and and in these days
you know one does backups to hard drives
anyway not the tape so it's sort of it
conceptually a replication is sort of
like a rolling backup that it's always
there one thing you do get into though
then is that if I if you sort of
fat-finger the system right like say you
drop a collection or table it's gonna
that's going to get replicated right so
you lose it everywhere no matter how
many machines you had so you do you
still probably want backups for that
reason in addition any piece of software
could have a bug and maybe that
percolates through all the replicas too
so that would be a good reason having
backup to also an in MongoDB we have a
feature we call slave delay which means
that a replica you can force a replica
to stay behind real time a desired
amount like you could say I want this
replica the state eight hours behind
real time or four hours behind real time
and it'll sort of be a rolling but back
up from that far into the past and that
way if you do have a situation where say
fat-finger the system you can go to the
replicas which is slave delayed and get
the data back the difference between a
backup and a replicas in is there's a
spectrum between them yeah I mean a
replica for you know whereas in in the
context here of data safety of replicas
is is basically a rolling backup now
there's other advantages replications
such as AJ and
and also in some cases a little scaling
up a bit but in terms of data safety
it's it's effectively a rolling back up
it's also a back up that can be brought
online quickly right because if with a
conventional backup you do the backup
you know the restore may take a while
too whereas the replicas could very
quickly take over almost instantly I
think we may get more into this later
because I have some questions
specifically about but with
does it have the ability to identify
when right note has gone down and to
bring one of the replicas online as a
master it does so and in the this
style replication we do is is sort of a
synchronous master slave or primary
secondary replication to me there's at
least three flavors the replication one
can do the first is synchronous
replication so if you have two servers
sitting side-by-side with a very
high-speed connectivity network between
them that's a very low latency Network
between them you could just do
synchronous replication where you're
effectively doing a distributed commit
over those two nodes and servers so
they're always perfectly in sync so
that's been done with various databases
in the past however we didn't want to do
synchronous replication because you know
we want MongoDB to work well on
commodity hardware we want it to work
well in the cloud right where you you
may have some latency on the network and
we also wanted it to work well the
replication and when you're
replicating over a wide area network so
you know in if you have a database
in in California you could easily
replicate it
over the internet or over your own
network to say New York or Europe or
Asia and that would work just fine
because the replication is asynchronous
and and so as I mentioned we we're doing
what I would call asynchronous
master-slave replication which is is
pretty traditional you know product like
MySQL can do that there's another thing
you could do which is you can do
asynchronous master master replicas
and some of the new SQL products do that
that's when you get into more of
eventual consistency semantics we wanted
to have some strong consistency and
immediate consistency semantics
available so so that's why we've stuck
to more of a primary secondary approach
in you can query the slave or
secondaries if you say I'm ok with
eventually consistent reads but writes
always go to the primary so you
mentioned the master slave and master
master those are probably the two more
common topologies
talk a lil more about some of the
complexities with master master
topologies right well well with master
master really the problem it would be
conflicting rights so maybe you should
just define master master first and then
then I'll ask you that question again
ok so master master replication I would
consider to be a system where you can
write to any replica at any time would
be a good example of that and that means
that writes will be arriving at
different servers in the cluster
concurrently on different machines and
in fact maybe even when the network
partition the different servers are
getting receiving rights and processing
them so so what can happen then is that
you could have the same document on
different servers being manipulated in
different ways at the same time and then
what we're gonna have to do later is
somehow reconcile those manipulations of
those documents right so so if over here
we have a document and let's take an
example of let's say you're doing an
e-commerce site and a shopping cart
right and and on on one server there's
an Add to Cart for given cart no no no
another server there's another Add to
Cart and on another server there was a
remove from cart right so so we now have
three versions of this cart object and
they're all different and when we when
we replicate asynchronously and this
data is going to flow back and forth the
question is how do we reconcile those
versions
and generally what we would want to do
there is you would want the kind of to
add the carts to both show up in the
cart and remove to go away from the cart
but it's the developer may have to write
some custom version reconciliation code
to make that happen right because if if
we just use a strategy with with this
master master replication of last right
wins you know that's not what we would
want in this example right you know if
the last operation was the second Add to
Cart we wouldn't want to throw away the
other two operations on the cart there's
some complexities in these master master
topologies that you don't have in master
slave and there's no general solution to
how you solve them in the master master
case right I mean there's good patterns
for how you address it but I think in
many cases they require some effort on a
developer's part and they also require
care on the developer's part to not make
mistakes because in in a lot of a lot of
times in eventual a consistent system
99% of the time it's immediately
consistent so it's possible that kind of
in your testing that you're not really
exercising the eventual consistency
aspects of it and then all of a sudden
later you know it passes all the QA you
get in production that actually happens
you know you then you would have a
situation that you haven't q8 so it
would be important in those systems to
be sure to actually test the eventual
consistency in QA and staging by forcing
a delay between the servers or a
partitioning between the server's in
that environment before you get into
production so so there are some nuances
now there are also some advantages so in
ventral consistency makes it easier to
do multi data center configurations for
example so so there are pros and cons
but I think for the developer there's a
little more thinking in nuance when you
go to those things in addition there
there are some problems I think it's
just not there are some use cases for
it's just not the right way to go so for
example let's say you're building
something like Twitter and you want
people to sign up and specify a user
name
right and they're either gonna get the
username when they register are you
gonna say sorry that names already and
you just give me another one
that's a situation where you need strong
consistency semantics right because we
can't have two people allocated the same
username at the same time on different
servers and think they both have you
know the name Joe one two three
that would be bad and that so that would
be very hard to to solve I think with a
pure eventually consistent model you
mentioned a few minutes ago that in a
replicate system there are situations
where the programmer or the client has
to pin a particular read to the master
to get the level of consistency they
need for that operation right so in
MongoDB by default all reads and writes
go to the primary so you don't have to
do anything special you'll get kind of
this amman actually would have expected
in a traditional database by default and
then if you want to do reads from
secondaries or slaves you have to
explicitly say you have to explicitly
request that on your on your connection
to a database and say I'm okay with
slavery's then it will that the driver
will use the the secondaries in the
cluster for reads and spread up the
reads automatically so by default
everything would go to the primary so
there's no surprises and no matter which
configuration you have chosen for a
given connection to the database the
writes will always go to the primary
because the primary is the only node
that will accept the write in our model
you stated that the multi mastery of
eventual consistency isn't that also the
case with a master slave because of
latency that it's not fully consistent
yeah that that's a very good point so
it's the the slave if you're doing
asynchronous replication your slaves are
eventually consistent but if we don't do
any failover we could still have strong
consistency semantics so if you imagine
using MySQL you have a master in slave
you can do the Twitter registration
thing right even though you do have a
slight
it's just in a question of what am I
using the slave for right if the slave
is only doing reads of registrations
it's fine because we you know when
you're grabbing a username that's only
happening on the primary now the tricky
part which comes in then is how you do
failover right so if you were using
MySQL you know the or Oracle or
something doing asynchronous replication
you have a master in the slave and let's
go back to our kind of Twitter style
registration example and the master goes
down right now maybe you want to cut
over to the slave well the challenge is
that the slave might have been because
it's asynchronous behind the master in
terms of applying rights you know maybe
it's two milliseconds behind or maybe
longer depending on situation but there
is some window greater than zero where
it's probably behind so the the
challenge is if you do cut over you know
maybe somebody registered to one two
three in those two milliseconds and now
you're at risk of it wasn't on the old
slave that's now the primary somebody
else could come in and register it again
right so so this is a problem with
failover and databases that we've had
for a long time with whenever we've done
asynchronous replication it's not a new
problem it's an old problem if you were
doing synchronous replication you would
be fine but that has a lot of
limitations so so this is a thing that
we've thought about a lot and and we've
we have a model that we like for it
so in MongoDB there there's this we we
have a concept we call replica sets
interrupt the set is a cluster machines
where any of the machines can be primary
any machines can be secondary and with a
shared-nothing model they will elect the
primary and then the others will be
secondaries and if the primary goes down
there will be god mac failover there's
also automatic recovery of a failed
primary when it comes back up later now
then the question is well what about
that that latency because of
asynchronous replication so for our
model for if you if you have an
important right like the one we were
talking about on the registration what
we allow the user to do is to request
acknowledgement of the right
only when the right has reached a
majority of the members of the replica
sets right so in other words I get my
act back not when it's been written on
them on the primary or master but when
it's made it to more than one node in
the cluster and it in it turns out you
know with replica sets that if if a
right has made it to a majority two
members of the set you then guaranteed
you'll never lose the right because a
primary will never be elected unless a
majority has set us up so if you have
three members of the set ie you have a
replication factor of three right so
we're gonna have three total copies of
the data at any one point in time one
know they'll be primary and two will be
secondary
if one know this down and two are up we
still have majorities so we can elect
their primary if two notes are down and
one is up we don't have them a majority
so if if we get acknowledgement from a
majority of the members of a replica set
we know then we have a cluster white
commit and the data will never be lost
even though we're doing asynchronous
replication and and that's sort of the
model in MongoDB this approach you're
describing to me it sounds a lot like
two-phase commit or synchronous
replication would that be fair the the
right will occur immediately on the on
the primary and then asynchronously to
the slaves it is a little bit like
synchronous replication and that if you
ask for an acknowledgment after it
reaches majority in those you're going
to wait till it hits those other nodes
so in that sense it's the same but the
the interesting thing is you can kind of
mix right so you may have some rights
that aren't so important and you just do
them you you know they're gonna
percolate out but maybe you don't care
if you lose you know the last five
milliseconds of Rights for that
particular use case but your your point
is you can choose based on each instance
of a right how appropriate it is for a
given level of guaranteed of how secure
that right is right and exactly so and
and you can also I think it's just a
little bit of a generalization because
you know I might have a cluster where
where some of the nodes are on a land
locally so you can get pretty fast
acknowledgments but maybe one or more
are in the second data center for
disaster recovery or something and that
acknowledgments going to be slow so if
we waited for everyone to act it could
be quite slow but if we waited for just
the majority to act maybe it's fast so
so it's sort of a that's a little bit of
a hybrid but we still do achieve you
know cluster wide commit in in that
situation it's it's also a little
different from from synchronous in that
we we're doing basically read
uncommitted read semantics so if if if
an items been written through the
primary it may not have been written yet
to the secondary if you then read from
the primary you will see it right but if
it hasn't made it to the secondaries and
the primary crashes it would be lost
because the cluster white commit had not
yet occurred potentially so but you you
could read that so so unlike pure
synchronous replication you you you're
getting read uncommitted read semantics
and and I think in a lot of traditional
databases you can request that but it
doesn't default to that and so there's
some pros and cons to that so first of
all ideally you'd want read committed
semantics but that's the downside of the
small of the upside is then is that is
that we don't have a lot of locking
going on and a lot of waiting going on
for these other nodes to to process the
data right so if we wrote to a document
and and and it needs to percolate out if
you have this read commended semantics
we would not no one else could then
query it until it had percolated out so
so so there's some some pros and cons to
this model but in the world real world
it works well for a number of problems
you mentioned earlier that Geographic
redundancy is one of the use cases for
replication and did I understand that
within a replica set you can have nodes
within different data centers belonging
to the same MongoDB replica
how would you size a cluster to be
distributed across two data centers
would you put half of the nodes in each
one or do you put one and the remote
data center just as a failover yet you
could do either so it's really up to the
kind of system designer and the problem
they're trying to solve so one model
would be to have a couple of servers in
the primary data center right and then
if one of those fails the other one can
take over right so it's sort of a an H a
scenario there and then in addition to
have another member of the set that's in
the the D our data center and that's
really just for disaster recovery so
maybe you don't want to ever fail over
to that node but it's there for data
safety purposes so you can interrupt a
cassette configure a member and say I
never want this node to be primary if
you just want that behavior you could
also say well maybe it can be primary if
everyone else is down right but in
general I don't want it to be because
it's far away and it'll be slow to
access you you only have one master at a
given time so it's got the master is
going to be in one data center yes if
you're doing writes the other data
center they have to go over the network
to the remote location and then back
right so the write would correct and you
talked about configuring nodes so that
they can never be masters there's a
replica set have the ability to
differentially configure each node based
on what roles you'd like it to be
nominated for yes it does have that
capability and in general the preferred
way to use it is to have as little
special configuration as possible but
really just say here are the members
they're all kind of peers they can all
do the same thing and it's it's there's
no single point of failure they'll just
select the primary and do what they need
to do the the upcoming release is a
MongoDB will have some new support for
data center awareness so that it's
easier to kind of get the behaviors you
want so for example if you were doing
you did say I'm okay with eventually
consistent reads it would then all the
math they talk to servers from the
replica set they're nearby general when
you have multiple read replicas and not
necessarily limited to MongoDB how do
reads get distributed among the replicas
well you could I think the common case
if you are reading from the secondaries
would be that they could be round-robin
they're randomly sent to any secondary
for example or a connection from a
client would be either on the ground
robin basis or randomly sent to a
particular secondary would be the way
that that's balanced out in addition
some some users have a primary and a
secondary they do all operations against
the primary the secondary is really
they're just kind of a hot standby hot
backup ready to take over if the primary
fails that's another way to use it one
thing to think about is if you imagine a
system like let's say we have two
servers right so we have primary and a
secondary you know you could say well I
think I'll send some reads to the
secondary right because that'll give me
more capacity but the only thing is if
you lose a node and and the other one
takes over is primary you only have one
node up then and the question would then
be well can it handle the full load
right because we were using two servers
to handle full node on the failover
event sort of you know in this impulse
one scenario we're only going to use one
server and do we have enough capacity
because our common case is both servers
are up you know having really measured
that one server can handle the load and
if one server can't handle the load well
why do we even bother to send the reads
to the other node anyway so so so that
there are some nuances there and sort of
capacity planning with I think any
system where you know you got to make
sure that you have the right amount of
capacity if you lose a server and you
know if you have 100 servers you know
losing a server isn't a big deal but if
you have to you know you lost a lot of
capacity capacity planning you would
want to think about how many servers do
I have and how many could I lose right
and and you know the a lot of people
talk about n + 1 where
you know if I need n servers to run I
have n plus one servers so I can lose
one and if you have very large number of
machines you would want to have more
than one extra server because with a lot
of machines there's significant
probability losing more than one at the
same time I want to get a little bit
under the hood on how replication works
do replicate is it more common that the
master is pushing updates out to the
replicas or the replicas connecting to
the master and pulling the updates from
the master
so in MongoDB the model is that the the
secondaries will pull data from the
master at whatever rate they can take it
and so they'll kind of there's there's
this concept in in the database of an op
log or an operation log which is really
a log of all rights which have occurred
and and and that's sort of like a
circular queue of rights which are
occurring on the primary the the
secondaries will then basically tail
that queue and and apply those items
locally and hopefully they're keeping up
and and they're applying them almost
immediately but if they weren't and
keeping up or maybe they were down
either for planned mate and that's or
unplanned they they'll catch up when
they come back online as long as the opt
log was big enough that goes back far
enough in time that they can sync back
up does the replication impose any
significant load on the master yeah
that's interesting
not very much surprisingly right so so
we're running to this off log but the
rights to that op log are sequential
rights so so there's a little bit of
overhead there and then the the
secondaries are querying this data from
the primary right the from the off log
but they're really just tailing the end
of the out log right so they're really
just hitting data that's in RAM and
they're and they're pulling it sort of
kind of sequential off the tail of the
collection of the aqua collection so
it's actually pretty efficient so it
turns out in practice that the overhead
is is is actually fairly low is there
any number of replicas where the
overhead would
start to be significant or is that not
really the limiting factor in how many
replicas you would have well it would be
significant probably if you had ten
replicas let's say in that in a replica
set but even then it's not too bad
because they're all going to be telling
the same they're all going to be say
give me the end of the off log which is
in RAM so I need to shoot it out to all
of them but it's pretty easy because
they're all asking for the same thing
it's in RAM and I'm still only riding at
once on the primary through the op log
no matter how many there are
so it actually scales up pretty well I
mean the I think the the Leming factor
is really just that there isn't a good
great reason to have a lot of replicas
right you know you might want you might
want more than two let's say three just
four have more data safety and higher
availability so you could potentially
lose more than one machine you know you
can imagine having five copies maybe if
you're doing a lot of reads from
secondaries but generally it would be
unusual to go higher than that even
though you can't are the replicas
polling the master then yes they're
basically tailing the OP log on them on
the primary and in a replica set you
have you have automatic failover and
recovery from failures in the set so
what will happen is is there will be
this contaminant continual polling of
each member in the set of the other
members and they will then notice if a
note is down in particular if the
primaries down and if everyone is seeing
that the primary is down there will be a
new election so if a majority of nodes
think that the primaries the old primary
is down they will elect one of
themselves as the new primary and take
over and how does that election process
work it's it's just a peer-to-peer kind
of consensus election protocol it's what
we did is is pretty simple it would be a
little bit like a Paxos algorithm but
we're actually doing something a little
simpler and a little and slightly less
efficient
because the elections are infrequent so
so it's not a it's not it necessary
really to make it perfectly optimal it's
just got to be correct what would happen
if the former master came back online
and found it was no longer the master
exactly that's a great question so
imagine let's take the example again of
a traditional database like MySQL and we
have a master and a slave right let's
say the master went down right and that
we cut over to the slave and we promoted
it to be a master right then we do a
bunch of rights to it now let's say our
old master we we fixed whatever was
wrong there and we bring it back up and
we'd like to get it back on line
well the challenge is there was probably
because the replication was asynchronous
there was probably a few rights that hit
the old master before the the new one
took over so it's in an inconsistent
state this is the multi master problem
all over again
right so so there's then two options one
option is the DBA could say you know I
those few rights in that little interval
there I don't really need them so what
I'm going to do is I'm just going to
make the old master be consistent with
the new master state now unfortunately
to do that what probably means with a
traditional database you need to do a
full image copy back to the old master
which is not ideal the other thing you
could do is you could manually is the
DBA try to merge the data yourself so
you can do that but you need to you can
imagine that taking like a full day to
do and give them with mommy ODB we want
to be able to build large clusters will
save thousands jeans you know machines
are going to be failing and coming back
up all the time so we need a solution
that that's completely automated it
doesn't require a bunch of DBA after it
on a fell over and recovery so that's
why we've got the replica set model so
you have those two options so kind of
full image copy from the new master or
manual DBA merging traditionally so what
we did with replica sets is is we
basically did something analogous to the
first scenario which is say I'm just
going to drop the data for those few
milliseconds that it was sort of a flag
and and if that was important you should
have asked for acknowledgement from
majority and you can and then the
question is just how do we quickly get
that old master back up right we don't
want to do a full image copy so what we
actually do is is when that note comes
up it'll say it'll see the other nodes
and it'll say hey I'm out of sync you
know I'm coming back up there's been a
failover there's been other rights
elsewhere the old primary will then roll
back the operations it had written in
that small interval of time that never
made it out the door making it then
consistent with a previous point in time
from the rest of the cluster and then it
will as a secondary start applying items
that were written while it was down and
getting back caught up so you can very
very quickly having a server recover in
a MongoDB replica set and get back up
and in sync with very little effort
which which is nice
how could you characterize the size of
the OP log either in terms of so many
minutes of data or bytes of data the the
size of the OP log you need depends on
how fast you're writing right so so
let's say you want a secondary to be
able to be down for an hour right and
then be able to come back up and catch
up
so we then need to have an applause that
will store at least an hour's worth of
Rights right so if you're writing very
little it your op log probably doesn't
need to be very big the store and hours
worth of writes if you're writing
massive amounts of data though you could
have written a giant amount of data in
and out and and maybe you want more than
an hour you maybe you want three days
right maybe you want if it's servers
down for 8 hours or 24 hours they can
sync back up so generally you want a
pretty big off log and in terms of disk
you know in terms of space on on disk
drives you know disk is cheap right so
so our general thinking is make the op
log very big you know from a storage
perspective disk is cheap from an you
know iOS per second perspective disk is
expensive right so so the thing we need
here is space not
i OS per second so so we would recommend
using a large allocation for the app log
and in fact I believe the default I log
size if you do not request particular
size is about 5% of the total beta
volume size so if you had a terabyte
drive we'd actually take 50 gigabytes
for the OP log by default what you're
trying to save by having a bigger up log
is the situation where you have to
rebuild a full image of the database
right so imagine I have a terabyte data
drive right our data volume if if I'm
too stale to catch up I didn't need to
copy everything over in which in this
case would mean copying over a terabyte
of information right so we wouldn't want
to do that so we'd like to catch up from
a clog if we could I'd rather pull over
50 gigabytes than a terabyte and that
would be much nicer this blog contain
the statements that were applied to the
database or is it some more compact form
that can be written directly into the
disk it the applicant Eanes the log the
logical writes that basically happened
on the primary and and so it's not
necessarily a more compact format but in
some cases it is pretty compact so if
you inserted a new document the whole
document would appear in the OP log but
if you did a partial update to a
document in MongoDB like let's say you
just set one field the actual dollar
sign set of one field is what will be an
applaud which is quite small so you may
have a very large you know let's say you
have a document it's 300 kilobytes one
document you know if I just increment an
integer in it then the the data in the
OP log for that increment will be quite
small and and that an important point
there is which I think I already said
implicitly is that is that the the
applaud for replication is a logical
level rather than at a low level
physical level because there's two ways
you could do replication first you could
you could store in in a
a transaction log or redo log if you
will high-level write operations to the
database or you could still store very
low level physical writes to the data
file so you can say okay this file this
offset this length these bytes right you
know so that's one style it's sort of
this low-level writing of you know the
actual file items and then the other
style is very high level you know insert
this document in this collection and
without specifying any anything further
so in we're doing the high-level
logical version and and we like that
because that means that the primary and
the secondaries don't have to actually
have the data in exactly the same
physical file locations so for example
if you if you wanted to do a compaction
or repair of a copy of the database on
one server the other that will then if
you did a compaction you know things
moved around the system is not going to
mind then when you when you afterwards
because at the logical level they still
have the same data in addition let's say
you upgraded to a new version of one of
the notes the system will generally be
okay with the fact that that server one
has one version and server two has
another version and if they don't
actually store the data exactly the same
way on disk that's okay you know and
some if you do the low-level logging you
know what you typically have to do if
you do a system upgrade if you have to
upgrade all of the nodes in the cluster
at the same time and you can't run mixed
versions so doing it logical level we
can support that talked earlier about
partitioning data charting data in order
to get scalability would you then not
want to replicate each shard for reason
of backup or availability of each shard
definitely so in Monga the way we think
about the problem is is we think of
replication and sharding as being
orthogonal so we think a replication is
really being about data safety and H
and as sharding as being the way to
scale up right so sharding is basically
partitioning its order preserving
partitioning so so if your Chardon on
the particular key keys that are close
together in the key range will tend to
be on the same server which has some
nice properties but basically we're
partitioning so a given document in in
the database will be on one and only one
sharp right so so it's partitioning
right every every shard has different
data with replication it's exactly the
opposite we want the replicas to be
identical right so so what happens with
with is you will you have some
number of shards and then for each shard
you'll typically have a replica set
within that shard so if a machine if a
machine within that shards replica set
fails there's failover available if
people would like to find out more about
MongoDB how can they do that
and go to the website so MongoDB that
ork there's a ton of Doc's there and and
there's also presentations including
videos video presentations on
replication sharding entry of the
things like that or just jump in the IRC
or the forums and ask a question if
people would like to find out about
Tenjin what's the best way Tenjin is is
a company that's commercializing MongoDB
we began the project but it's an open
source project now so yeah so if you
want to use it for free it's highly
encouraged for the MongoDB you.org and
do that if you want some commercial
support and services go to pension comm
and we can help you there for the sort
of enterprise you know 24 by 7
production support and advisory
consulting and things like that do you
blog or tweet or how can people follow
your thoughts yep so the there's a
MongoDB blog which we'll find from the
site and then
and MongoDB is the twitter handle for
and and then I think mine is DM er
R and I also recommend if event
comes to your city I've been to the last
one in San Francisco and there are very
very good events so that wraps things up
thank you for talking to software
engineering radio thanks thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
dotnet to support us you can advertise
se radio by clicking the Digg reddit
delicious or slash dive buttons on the
site well by talking about us on
Facebook Twitter or your own blog we've
got feedback specific to an episode
please use the commenting feature on the
site so other listeners can respond to
your comments as well listen all of the
episodes of se radio is licensed under
the creative commons two-point-five
license please see the website for
details thanks again for your support